hey what's up guys my name is a Cherno
and welcome back to my c++ series so
today we're gonna be talking all about
macros in c++ and we're just gonna have
like a basic kind of overview of this
I'm not gonna get too deep into this
today we'll have some future episodes
where we really dive into specifically
like specific scenarios of where macros
can help you out and probably some
advanced examples as well but today
we're just going to introduce them and
talk about what they actually are so
what does the C++ macro macro is is such
a broad term that you could you may have
heard other definitions of what a macro
actually is in C++ but what I'm
specifically talking about today is
using the preprocessor in C++ to kind of
macro fie certain operations right so
instead of asked manually having to type
out some kind of code over and over
again we can use the preprocessor to
actually help us automate that in some
sense so if you don't know what the
preprocessor the ears I did make a video
a while back about how this people's
last compiler works that covers that
some extent so definitely click up there
and check that out if you haven't
already but basically when we compile a
C++ program one of the first things that
happens is a preprocessor pass occurs in
which basically every every kind of
statement that you see in C++ those
tasks with a hash is known as a
preprocessor directive that gets
evaluated and kind of done right and
then that code gets passed on to the
compiler for the actual compilation and
all of that stuff
so this preprocessor stage is basically
a text editing stage in which we can
kind of control what code actually gets
fed to the compiler and that's where
macros come in what we can do is write
some kind of macro that basically
replaces text in our code with something
else right so it's basically like going
through our code and performing a find
and replace and this doesn't just have
to be a flat kind of just a straight
find/replace
it can be a fine in replace with kind of
parameters and arguments and variables
and all of that so we can actually kind
of customize the way that we call that
macro we'll define how like what it
actually expands to and this can be
extremely complicated we talked about
templates recently and with Ted I mean
the thing with that is this is this is a
bit different because this doesn't
happen during like templates get
evaluated a bit later right in the
actual compilation this is just the
preprocessor and this is pure text like
replacing so there's really like you
can't really there's nothing you can
there's nothing you can't not replace
because it's it's before everything gets
compiled right but what I'm kind of
getting at is that there is a lot of
stuff that you can actually do here and
it can be really simple it can be really
complicated it can be really annoying it
can be really useful and the way that
you use this because their boss calls
itself such a powerful language the way
that you use this and limit yourself is
kind of going to be up to I guess your
personal opinion and your personal
preference I don't like overusing macros
because it's very hard for people who
read your code for the first time to
understand what everything means and
it's just not useful oh like a lot of
the time don't feel with a lot of these
C++ pages especially as we get into the
more advanced ones there's a tendency
for new program is to just really really
use them a lot um and I said this in the
templates video as well like that's you
shouldn't be trying to do that right
don't feel you have to use every single
say philosophy sure to write your
program like there's no point you that's
not how that's not how that's not how
you write good code right you're not
trying to show off and right absolutely
just show everyone that you know every
single zip ocelots feature out there
you're trying to write good code I would
hope so just a little kind of precursor
to this don't feel you have to use all
this anyway I'm gonna I'm gonna ramble
on here for hours if we don't get into
some code so let's get into some code
and talk about macros and how they work
and all that okay so I have a very basic
program here and let's think about
creating our first macro so this STD
syndicate is something that when I run
my program will actually do is kind of
pause the execution over here like this
until I hit the enter key and then it
actually closes my program so this line
basically waits for some kind of Enter
key press because it needs to read in a
line from the console what we can do is
instead of having to write SDC end up
get every single time we can define a
mapper
basically just insert that code in so
the way we do that is we write hash
define okay this can be written anywhere
by the way I'm choosing to write it up
here because it's a sensible place let's
just say wait and then we'll define that
to be STD CN get just like that and I'm
not going to define a semicolon and I'll
tell you why in a minute
okay now what we can do is basically get
rid of this line and just type in weight
followed by a semicolon okay now if I
hit f5 you can see we get these SM
result and two key press close
everything so what I've basically done
is said that whenever you encounter this
symbol write the word wait I want you to
paste in this code so what happens is
during the preprocessor during the
compilation stage and during the pre
presenting stage this basically gets
replaced like that and that is the code
that actually gets sent to the compiler
which is of course what we had before so
you can see how this mapper has
essentially as far as that program the
way that our program runs and what our
compiler sees and how it gets compiled
identical compulsions don't see any
difference because what we've actually
done is we've just changed the way that
the text kind of gets generated as it
gets sent to the compiler hopefully that
makes sense okay so this is super the
example I've just shown you I really
hope none of you ever do it because this
is not this is not how you use the pre
process this is silly you should write
STD sandor get absolutely you should
write the actual code because what
happens is if this was defined in a
different file right then all you would
see in this file is kind of just dad
right you'll see that he was to just see
wait and what what on earth does why it
means now this requires the programmer
to actually look up the weight symbol
that you've got somewhere else in your
code and be like ah I see it's STD and
get right you're not trying to write
confusing code this isn't like some kind
of obfuscation competition I hope so
don't don't use the preprocessor this
way anyway back to this you might have
noticed that I kind of played around
with a semicolon the reason I didn't put
a semicolon here is because I wanted to
put one here kind of makes more sense if
you
or semicolons here in a sense right what
you can do is not put a semicolon here
of course that causes a syntax error
because now the code that we actually
have is that and we do need a semicolon
at the end of this statement and we can
just move the semicolon into here make
it part of the macro now you can see
this looks even weirder we don't need a
semicolon
if we can put one here but this just
evaluates to kind of being an empty
statement as if it wasn't another line
like this right okay
few more things we don't this isn't just
limited to actual statements or I mean
it can be any code it can be this but it
also could be something as trivial as
you know a curly bracket and we could
call this maybe open curly right open
curly and now what we can do let's
restore our seeing key over here now
what we can do is replace this with open
curly all right and this is looking
ridiculous but if we compile and run our
code of course it's going to be fine
right because what it's done is when the
preprocessor sees this code it will
replace this open curly word with this
bracket like that and we get a normal
program again now that example don't use
the preprocessor this way right unless
you're trying to write confusing code in
which case I guess this is a decent
example well they probably wouldn't be
calling it open curly anyway but the
point is this is how the preprocessor
works I'm showing you all this so that
you understand how it works now let's
get into maybe some useful code so
another thing that you can actually do
is send parameters in okay so suppose
that I wanted to basically automate this
kind of STD see out you know I wanted to
basically just write this right so I
wanted to have hello printing I didn't
want to have to write esidisi out it's a
bit awkward to type whoops it's a bit
awkward to type because I have to type
out these like less than symbols and
whatever gets a bit annoying so what I'm
going to do is define a macro called log
that will basically log something i've
written x over here and this will kind
of expand to STD see out x and then end
line and again I'm not writing a
semicolon here because I want to have
one in my actual macro now I can replace
this with log hello like that and you
can probably guess what's gonna happen
here when the preprocessor goes through
this it will basically replace log with
that right and then look at this
parameter and you can see x over
I'm using over here right so it's going
to copy and paste whatever is in here
and just put it over here and so we
basically just end up with this which is
exactly what we want right so if I run
my code right now as it is we will get
holo printing to the console so this is
kind of warming up towards where I might
use a macro right I wouldn't really
probably use long we'll see out in this
fashion however in more complicated
logging systems if you've got like a
game engine or an application or some
kind of framework you are likely to have
logging systems that you want to have as
macros because the way that the logging
kind of is defined may change based on
your configuration so let's take it
let's take a look at an example of that
we have two configurations right now in
our program we have debug and we have
released debug with is useful for
debugging right that's potentially as
we're developing our code as we're
developing our application we want to
actually run it in a way that is not
optimized and potentially has extra code
in there that will help us debug our
actual code and so that we can like I
said not optimize just so that we can
like kind of go through breakpoints and
actually like so the compiler doesn't
transform our code to marching it in an
attempt to optimize it so that we can
actually debug it properly as is so
anyway logging is a great example in
debug mode we potentially want
absolutely everything to be locked
however in release mode we definitely
don't want that to happen because first
of all maybe release mode is our
distribution build right that's what we
actually distribute that's what we
actually send out to people who aren't
developers to our actual users we don't
want that to be logging for a number of
reasons maybe we don't want to give out
any kind of secret information in those
log files or in the actual logging meant
we're printing something that we don't
really want to actually print right but
also performance logging takes time and
we definitely don't want to be wasting
time logging messages to a console
during you know a user who doesn't care
about that actually like playing a game
or using our application so what we
might actually want to do is strip all
of the logging code from our actual
release builds but keep them in debug
builds and we can actually do that using
a mapper so what I can do is if I
right-click on hello world and hit
properties hello world is name of my
project
I've got debug and release under my
configurations I'm going to go into C
C++ preprocessor
and I'm actually going to define some
thing at the front over here called
debug alright now this is this may may
or may not be defined based on your
compiled it might be like underscore
debug or something like that it may
already be defined but it might not be
which is why I'm showing you guys how to
actually define it yourself I'm actually
going to call this something like PR
underscore debug PR is just gonna be two
little letters that is like the name of
our project it stands for project in
this case but maybe if I was working on
the Sparky game engine which is a game
engine I wrote I might be using SP
underscore debug just to basically be
like this is my macro right so it
doesn't kind of it's like a namespace
almost so that it doesn't clash with
other mappers so I've defined something
in the preprocessor called PR debug and
and in release I'll save this I might
define something called PR release now
for this example we might not need this
but in other examples you may want to
actually have that so what I'm going to
do now is I'm going to write a basic if
def if def PR underscore debug I'm going
to basically include this code otherwise
so else I'm going to write define log X
and I'm actually not gonna put anything
there just like that
okay now there's plenty wrong with this
code which I'll explain in a minute but
that's the basic example so if PR debug
is defined we're going to include this
code otherwise we're going to include
this card now what do you think happens
when we have log X like this a macro
like that and then nothing after it it's
gonna replace it with nothing so what's
actually gonna happen is if PR debug is
not defined you can see Visual Studio is
actually highlighting the one that is so
if I just drop this down and change it
to release mode you can see this flips
this is what happens which means this
gets just removed like that okay I've
literally made it so that in release
built I am NOT including certain code in
compilation at all which is awesome
because it means that that log message
won't get triggered at all I'm not C
outing anything which means that I get
all of that slave performance back and
my log message beautiful let's test this
out so in debug mode just go back to
debug and hit f5 you can say get the
word holo printing to the console
awesome and then finally I'm just going
to change my configuration to release
not touching the code at all just change
my can
duration now I hit local windows
debugger on my code and check this out I
get absolutely nothing printing to the
console so that macro has gone ahead and
basically just removed code for me
that's really cool and that is actually
a really good use case that is used in
the real world all the time now there
are certain other ones that we can
actually use again for debugging
purposes which you might have now
actually I did say there was something's
wrong with this code and I know that
sometimes I end up being like hey
there's playing wrong with this code but
I'm not gonna tell you what it is so let
me just tell you what it is first of all
I'm using if def that's not great what I
probably would be doing is something
like if PR debug equals one and then I
would actually define PR debug to be an
actual value instead of actually you
know defining it the thing was like
defining is that if you misunderstand
something with macros you can generally
define symbols as either being you know
define PR underscore debug or maybe
define peons for the above one the
benefit of doing it this way means that
you can actually just put it back to
zero and you don't have to actually
remove the whole symbol by the
commenting it or actually removing it so
this is a lot more clear and if you
write your code this way you can see I
can actually control debug PR debug up
here now you can also do this of course
in the properties by just defining in
debug defining PR debug to be one like
that that's also totally fine and that
will mean obviously if this overrides
that but if I get rid of this code it
actually means that will include certain
code here
which works pretty well the other
problem here is that maybe that's not
really a problem but what we also could
have done is since I did define PR
release we can do else L if sorry L if
defined PR release like that and that
would actually be you know if release
might is to find a post baron release me
back to debug mode then everything would
be fine
over there okay and I'm actually gonna
go back here and fix my mistake
obviously I've put spaces in here you
can't do that so let's just leave it
like that and hit OK and there we go
that works just fine so that's basically
I guess the same thing that I did before
but just showing you guys another way to
do it using ear frog than if defined or
a depth which is slightly worse in a lot
of cases anyway I'm gonna wrap off the
video there because that is a pretty
basic
and tomorrow is actually one more thing
would this if thing what you can do is
disable entire blocks of code as well so
I could quickly just say if the zero
which means kind of if false and then
wrap some code in that like that now
this is now fully inactive right which
means of course I get an error in this
case but you can see that we can
actually use preprocessor and macros I
guess to actually get rid of certain
things in code I've got a few more
examples that I'm probably going to show
in more videos there are a lot of things
we can do here we can play around with
like string manipulation and we can
actually insert different built-in
kind of preprocessor symbols such as
what like file the statement is actually
it kind of inserted in writing and what
line of code it's happening in what
function it's in and stuff like that
there's a lot of stuff we can actually
do mostly for debugging purposes if I
have to be completely honest macros are
the most useful for debugging purposes I
also didn't mention that you can use
backslash as if you want multi-line
mappers in fact I guess I'll show you
one more example what you can do is if
you have something like let's just say
this whole main function I want to make
a macro out of this I don't have to
write it all in one line just being like
you know int main and then STD see and
whatever that might be annoying what I
can actually do is write int main and
then what I actually want another line I
can just add a backslash which basically
escapes the newline character when I hit
enter then I can write my opening curly
bracket and on the backslash and then
I'll write my STD seeing duck get no the
backslash and then this and then I can
basically replace this whole thing with
main just like that and if I run my code
you can see that it runs just fine as
before and I can just hit enter and
everything's great okay so the back
slashes are basically just escaping this
Enter key presses it's kind of not
feeding in that entered that newline
character into the pre process so that
actually so that it actually keeps
treating this as part of the same macro
if you didn't have this then this is
just kind of normal code right because
macro is kind of do have to be on one
line okay but backslash can prevent that
make sure you don't have a space after
your backslash because then you're
actually escaping the space and not
not the newline character so it has to
be backslash and then answer straight
away anyway
hope that kind of explains macros to the
best way to actually see these in action
is to see them in action
so when we start the game ends in series
and we I've already used them in the
OpenGL series actually check out the
video about OpenGL errors that has some
credit examples on how to actually use
macros we use one for actually like
wrapping every opengl function call in a
macro so that we can arrow check it
automatically every time we use in
opengl function definitely check that
out that's a real world example of how
you might use macros when we set the
game engine series as well plenty of
macros will be used don't worry for
stuff like memory allocation as well
really useful because another example
here that I might just give right now is
memory with memory allocation in debug
builds we might want to know exactly how
many bytes are being allocated from
which file and which line of code so
literally like please tell me is it
coming from mando CPP line 15 my
allocated 28 bytes I want to know that
kind of stuff right the tracking or for
just debugging purposes for whatever you
can actually use a macro to do that if
you replace the new keyword with like a
custom keyword which which will
automatically actually track which line
which file in line the allocation came
from and how big it was and all that
kind of stuff so that's another useful
kind of use case for macros anyway I
hope you guys enjoyed this video if you
did in that like button you can also
help support the series that I do here
on youtube by going to patron icon for
Sasha chana huge thank you as always to
everyone who helps support all these
videos because they wouldn't be here
without all those wonderful supporters
next time we're going to probably I
might just dive into some more advanced
map for a kind of examples actually but
there are quite a lot of things that I
still need to cover for the C++ series
if you want to say something specific
definitely leave a comment below and I
will see you next time goodbye
[Music]